Roger G. Newton papers, 1955-2003 C320
Indiana University Archives
Roger G. Newton papers
1955-2003
1970-1990
Indiana University Archives
Newton, Roger G.
C320
9 cubic feet 9 boxes
Roger G. Newton was a Distinguished Professor Emeritus of Physics at Indiana University. His primary research interests include field theory, scattering theories, nuclear and high energy physics, elementary particles, quantum mechanics, and mathematical physics. The collection consists of Newton's papers created and collected during his tenure at IU, including correspondence, files on committees and conferences, review board records and materials relating to his books. No teaching files are included in this collection.
Access Restrictions
Select files and the Reviews & evaluations series is closed to researchers at this time.
Advance notice is required for access.
Biographical Note
Roger Gerhard Newton was born in Landsberg on the Warthe, Germany, on November 30, 1924. His father, Arthur Newton, was a dentist and his mother was Margaret (Blume) Newton. He attended two engineering schools in Germany before attending the University of Berlin in 1946.
He married Ruth Gordon on June 18, 1953, while working as a member of the Institute for Advanced Study, in Princeton, New Jersey. The couple had three children: Julie, Rachel, and Paul.
In 1955, he came to Indiana University as an Assistant Professor, was promoted to Associate Professor in 1958, and reached the status of full Professor in 1960. While teaching at IU he also held visiting appointments at several universities and laboratories including Ohio State, University of Rome, International School of Physics, University of Montpellier in France, and the University of Geneva. He was also named director of IU's Institute of Advanced Study. Institutes of its kind are designed to foster pure cutting-edge research by scientists and scholars in a variety of fields without the complications of teaching or funding, or the agendas of sponsorship. The Institute was the first of its kind in the U.S. to be associated with an academic institution.
Newton's primary research interests were field theory, scattering theories, nuclear and high energy physics, elementary particles, quantum mechanics, and mathematical physics. In addition to authoring many articles and books including From Clockwork to Crapshoot: A History of Physics, Thinking about Physics, and What Makes Nature Tick?, Dr. Newton also served as the editor of the Journal of Mathematical Physics (1992-2005), and was associate editor of the American Journal of Physics and Inverse Problems.
Newton died on April 14, 2018 at the age of 93.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into seven series: Correspondence; Committees and organizations; ARO (Army Research Office) files; NSF (National Science Foundation) files; Writings; Conferences; and Reviews and evaluations. The Correspondence series is further organized into External correspondence, Internal correspondence, and General correspondence.
Scope and Content Note
The collection is arranged into seven series: Correspondence; Committees and organizations; ARO (Army Research Office) files; NSF (National Science Foundation) files; Writings; Conferences; and Reviews and evaluations. The Correspondence series is further organized into External mail, Internal mail and General mail.
The Correspondence series contains records from the years 1955-2000. Following Dr. Newton's original arrangement, the series is further organized into three subseries. The first subseries is Internal correspondence, 1969-2000. This subseries consists of Prof. Newton's with Indiana University administrators and colleagues, such as IU President Herman B Wells and Newton's colleagues in the physics department. The next subseries, External correspondence, 1969-1999, consists of correspondence with persons outside IU. Many of the letters are from former students and colleagues who are writing either for letters of recommendation or to ask questions about methods or theories relating to physics. The last subseries within the Correspondence series is General correspondence, 1955-1979. The letters found in this series are more personal in nature or are of a general nature, such as departmental memos. This series is arranged chronologically and closely follows Newton's original organization. He had all of the files organized by fiscal year, but as some were quite large, they were broken down by month in order to make the files more manageable for researchers.
The next series in the collection is entitled Committees and organizations, 1975-2003, and is arranged alphabetically by folder title. The committee folders contain correspondence between committee members, memos, and minutes of some of the meetings. The folders for the organizations contain much of the same materials, although some also contain pamphlets or business cards. Newton's records pertaining to the Indiana University Institute of Advanced Study are a prominent part of this series. Two folders in this series, "Committee to review dean of music school (Charles Webb)" and "Tenure committee," are restricted and not available for use by researchers at this time.
The third series in the Newton collection spans 1965-1975 and is the ARO (Army Research Office) files. This series includes paperwork for grants that Newton received from the Army Research Office on projects focusing on inverse scattering problems, phase transitions and critical points, lattice non-uniformities and localized magnetic moments in solids, and irreversible phenomena. Also found in the files are reports from Newton to the Army Research Office explaining his progress or any problems that he may have encountered while implementing these projects.
Records for Newton's NSF (National Science Foundation) projects make up the next series. Spanning 1968-1992, these projects focus projects related to elementary particle interactions, particle collisions, and the complex Regge Trajectory. The series includes correspondence between Newton, his colleagues, and the NSF, as well as project proposals and outlines. Detailed account statements were pulled and shredded.
The fifth series is entitled Writings, 1960-1992. The writings include works by Newton as well as articles written by his colleagues. This series also includes proofs of two of Newton's books, The Truth of Science and What Makes Nature Tick, complete with illustrations, notes, and corrections.
The next series is Conferences and consists of schedules, flyers, and pamphlets that Newton received from the various conferences that he attended during his career. Several folders in this series are labeled according to the name of the conference, but the bulk of the folders are simply labeled by year. It spans the years 1975-1987.
The last series in the collection is Reviews and evaluations. It is organized alphabetically by folder title and contains reviews of individuals, departments and programs both within and outside of Indiana University. At this time, this series is restricted and cannot be used by researchers.
Acquisition Information
Accessions 97/026 and 2006/042
Appraisal
Detailed financial statements were pulled from the NSF files and shredded.
Physicists --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Physicists --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Physics teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Archives.; Physics teachers --Indiana --Bloomington --Correspondence.; Newton, Roger G. --Archives.; Newton, Roger G. --Correspondence; Newton, Roger G. -- Archives; Newton, Roger G. -- Correspondence; Indiana University. Department of Physics -- Faculty -- Archives; Indiana University. Department of Physics -- Faculty -- Correspondence; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Physics -- Faculty -- Archives; Indiana University, Bloomington. Department of Physics -- Faculty -- Correspondence
- Correspondence, 1955-2000
  - Internal correspondence, 1969-2000
    Scope and Content Note
    There is no internal correspondence for academic year 1978-1979
    - 1969-1970 (Box 1)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 1)
    - Jan.-June, 1973 (Box 1)
    - July-Dec., 1973 (Box 1)
    - Jan.-June, 1974 (Box 1)
    - July-Dec., 1974 (Box 1)
    - Undated, (1973-1974) (Box 1)
    - July-Oct., 1974 (Box 1)
    - Nov.-Dec., 1974 (Box 1)
    - Jan.-March, 1975 (Box 1)
    - April-Dec., 1975 (Box 1)
    - Undated, (1974-1975) (Box 1)
    - July-Sept., 1975 (Box 1)
    - Oct.-Dec., 1975 (Box 1)
    - Jan.-March, 1976 (Box 1)
    - April-June, 1976 (Box 1)
    - March-Sept., 1976 (Box 1)
    - Oct.-Dec., 1976 (Box 1)
    - Jan.-March, 1977 (Box 1)
    - April-July, 1977 (Box 1)
    - Undated, (1976-1977) (Box 1)
    - July-Oct., 1977 (Box 1)
    - Nov.-Dec., 1977 (Box 1)
    - Jan.-March, 1978 (Box 1)
    - April-June, 1978 (Box 1)
    - Undated, (1977-1978) (Box 1)
    - April-Oct., 1979 (Box 1)
    - Nov.-Dec., 1979 (Box 1)
    - Jan.-March, 1980 (Box 1)
    - April-June, 1980 (Box 1)
    - Undated, (1979-1980) (Box 1)
    - 1980 (Box 1)
    - 1981 (Box 1)
    - Undated, (1980-1981) (Box 1)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 1)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 1)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 1)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 1)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 1)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 1)
    - 1987-1988 (Box 1)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 2)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 2)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 2)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 2)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 2)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 2)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 2)
    - 1996 (Box 2)
    - 1997 (Box 2)
    - 1998 (Box 2)
    - 2000 (Box 2)
  - External correspondence, 1969-1999
    - 1969 (Box 2)
    - 1970 (Box 2)
    - Undated, (1969-1970) (Box 2)
    - Jan.-June, 1970 (Box 2)
    - July-Dec., 1970 (Box 2)
    - Jan.-June, 1971 (Box 2)
    - July-Dec., 1971 (Box 2)
    - 1972 (Box 2)
    - 1973 (Box 2)
    - Undated, (1972-1973) (Box 2)
    - Jan.-Sept., 1973 (Box 2)
    - Oct.-Dec., 1973 (Box 2)
    - Jan.-June, 1974 (Box 2)
    - July-Dec., 1974 (Box 2)
    - Undated, (1973-1974) (Box 2)
    - Jan.-June, 1975 (Box 2)
    - July-Dec., 1975 (Box 2)
    - Undated, (1974-1975) (Box 2)
    - 1974 (Box 2)
    - Jan.-June, 1975 (Box 2)
    - July-Dec., 1975 (Box 2)
    - Jan.-June, 1976 (Box 2)
    - July-Dec., 1976 (Box 2)
    - Jan.-May, 1977 (Box 2)
    - Undated, (1976-1977) (Box 2)
    - March-Oct., 1977 (Box 2)
    - March-Oct., 1977 (Box 2)
    - Jan.-March, 1978 (Box 2)
    - April-July, 1978 (Box 3)
    - Undated, (1977-1978) (Box 3)
    - Sept.-Oct., 1978 (Box 3)
    - Nov.-Dec., 1978 (Box 3)
    - Jan.-May, 1979 (Box 3)
    - June-Sept., 1979 (Box 3)
    - Oct.-Dec., 1979 (Box 3)
    - Jan.-March, 1980 (Box 3)
    - Undated, (1979-1980) (Box 3)
    - 1980 (Box 3)
    - 1981 (Box 3)
    - Undated, (1980-1981) (Box 3)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 3)
    - 1982-1983 (Box 3)
    - 1983-1984 (Box 3)
    - 1984-1985 (Box 3)
    - 1985-1986 (Box 3)
    - 1986-1987 (Box 3)
    - 1987 (Box 3)
    - 1988 (Box 3)
    - Undated, (1987-1988) (Box 3)
    - 1988-1989 (Box 3)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 3)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 3)
    - 1991-1992 (Box 3)
    - 1992-1993 (Box 3)
    - 1993-1994 (Box 3)
    - 1994-1995 (Box 3)
    - 1996 (Box 3)
    - 1997 (Box 3)
    - 1998 (Box 3)
    - 1999 (Box 3)
  - General correspondence, 1955-1979
    - Dec. 1960- June 1961 (Box 3)
    - July-Dec., 1961 (Box 3)
    - 1962 (Box 3)
    - Undated, (1960-1962) (Box 3)
    - 1963 (Box 4)
    - Jan.-May, 1964 (Box 4)
    - Undated, (1963-1964) (Box 4)
    - June-Dec., 1964 (Box 4)
    - Jan.-April, 1965 (Box 4)
    - May-Dec., 1965 (Box 4)
    - Undated, (1964-1965) (Box 4)
    - 1965-1966 (Box 4)
    - Jan.-Oct., 1966 (Box 4)
    - Nov.-Dec., 1966 (Box 4)
    - Jan.-March, 1967 (Box 4)
    - April-June, 1967 (Box 4)
    - July-Dec., 1967 (Box 4)
    - Undated, (1966-1967) (Box 4)
    - Jan.-Oct., 1967 (Box 4)
    - Nov.-Dec., 1967 (Box 4)
    - Jan.-March, 1968 (Box 4)
    - April-June, 1968 (Box 4)
    - Undated, (1967-1968) (Box 4)
    - Jan.-June, 1968 (Box 4)
    - July-Dec., 1968 (Box 4)
    - Jan.-June, 1969 (Box 4)
    - July-Dec., 1969 (Box 4)
    - Undated, (1968-1969) (Box 4)
    - Jan.-June, 1970 (Box 4)
    - July-Dec., 1970 (Box 4)
    - Jan.-June, 1971 (Box 4)
    - "Old Mail" (Box 4)
      - 1955-1956 (Box 4)
      - 1957 (Box 4)
      - 1958 (Box 4)
      - 1959 (Box 4)
      - 1960 (Box 4)
      - Undated, (1955-1960) (Box 4)
    - Mail to Rome (Box 4)
      - 1962 (Box 4)
      - 1963 (Box 4)
      - Undated, (1962-1963) (Box 4)
    - Departmental Memos, etc. (Box 4)
      - July-Dec., 1971 (Box 4)
      - Jan.-June, 1972 (Box 4)
      - July-Dec., 1972 (Box 4)
      - Jan.-March, 1973 (Box 4)
      - April-June, 1973 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence (Box 4)
      - 1978 (Box 4)
      - Jan.-March, 1979 (Box 4)
      - April-June, 1979 (Box 4)
      - Undated, (1979) (Box 4)
- Committees and organizations, 1975-2003 (Box 5)
  - AAAS (American Association for the Advancement of Science) committee, 1981-1985 (Box 5)
  - Bloomington library committee, 1991-1992 (Box 5)
  - Capital campaign committee, 1978-1982 (Box 5)
  - Committee to review dean of music school (Charles Webb), 1983-1985 (Box 5)
    General
    RESTRICTED
  - Concerned Titled Professors, 1978-1982 (Box 5)
  - Core curriculum, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Curriculum committee and exam, 1965-1973 (Box 5)
  - Dean of Research, 1976 (Box 5)
  - Distribution committee (Box 5)
    - 1978-1979 (Box 5)
    - 1980 (Box 5)
    - undated (Box 5)
  - Educational Policies committee, 1991-1993 (Box 5)
  - Executive committee (Box 5)
    - 1979-1983 (Box 5)
    - 1984-1986 (Box 5)
    - undated (Box 5)
  - Graduate advising, 1988-1992 (Box 5)
  - Graduate curriculum committee, 1986-1991 (Box 5)
  - Gafs committee, undated (Box 5)
  - Gulf Research and Development Co., 1978-1980 (Box 5)
  - Halls Professorship committee, 1993-1994 (Box 5)
  - Heineman Prize Committee, 1991 (Box 5)
  - Improvement of teaching, 1988-1989 (Box 5)
  - Initiatives committee, 1989 (Box 5)
  - Invitations, 1978-1980 (Box 5)
  - IUIAS (Indiana University Institute for Advanced Study) (Box 5)
    - 1981-1985 (Box 5)
    - 1986 (Box 5)
    - 1987 (Box 5)
    - 1989 (Box 6)
    - 1990-1995 (Box 6)
    - 1996-2003 (Box 6)
    - undated (Box 6)
  - Patten committee (Box 6)
    - 1981-1982 (Box 6)
    - 1982 (Box 6)
    - 1983 (Box 6)
    - 1984 (Box 6)
    - undated (Box 6)
  - Phi Beta Kappa, 1989-1993 (Box 6)
  - Physics Library committee (Box 6)
    - Monthly reports, 1984-1991 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1984-1991 (Box 6)
  - Proposals, 1961-1971 (Box 6)
  - Science Advisory committee, 1975-1980 (Box 6)
  - Subcommittee of Policy Committee (grade inflation), 1974-1979 (Box 6)
  - Subcommittee questionnaire (budget allocations), 1977 (Box 6)
  - Task Force on priorities, 1991-1992 (Box 6)
  - Tenure committee (Box 6)
    FILES RESTRICTED
    - 1988-1989 (Box 6)
    - 1989-1990 (Box 6)
    - 1990-1991 (Box 6)
  - Undergraduate education committee (Box 6)
    - Formal reports, 1995 (Box 6)
    - Correspondence, 1997-1998 (Box 7)
    - undated (Box 7)
- ARO (Army Research Office) files, 1965-1975
  - Army contract, 1965-1970 (Box 7)
  - ARO application, undated (Box 7)
  - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - 1969-1971 (Box 7)
    - 1972-1973 (Box 7)
    - 1974-1975 (Box 7)
- NSF (National Science Foundation) files, 1968-1992
  - Correspondence (Box 7)
    - 1968-1969 (Box 7)
    - 1970-1971 (Box 7)
    - 1972-1975 (Box 7)
    - 1976-1982 (Box 7)
    - 1983-1991 (Box 7)
    - undated (Box 7)
  - NSF proposals (Box 7)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 7)
    - 1973-1976 (Box 7)
    - 1977-1984 (Box 7)
    - 1985-1992 (Box 7)
    - undated (Box 7)
- Writings, 1960-2002
  - A. Ramm (letters and proofs of writings by Ramm), 1985-1992 (Box 7)
  - Benjamin Book Company, 1963-1986 (Box 7)
  - Encyclopedia of Mathematical Physics, 2001-2002 (Box 7)
  - Impurities in R, 1989-1993 (Box 8)
  - Rohrlich/Fulton paper, 1960 (Box 8)
    Correspondence concerning problems with their paper
  - Somersalo, Erkki (Inverse Scattering for Standing Wave Solutions and the Schrodinger Equation), undated (Box 8)
  - Tenth book book-notes (The Malignant Descendents of Conventionalism), undated (Box 8)
  - Tenth book ms, undated (Box 8)
  - The Truth of Science, 8/6/96 (Box 8)
    - additional notes, corrections, and correspondence, 1996 (Box 8)
    - figures, 1996-1997 (Box 8)
    - manuscript, 1996 (Box 8)
    - proof, Jan. 17, 1997 (Box 8)
    - proof, March 30, 1997 (Box 8)
  - What Makes Nature Tick (Box 8)
    - book illustrations, undated (Box 8)
    - proofs, 1993 (Box 8)
- Conferences, 1975-1987
  - Bay area inverse scattering conference, 1986 (Box 8)
  - Conferences (Box 8)
    - 1975-1976 (Box 8)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 8)
    - 1980-1981 (Box 8)
    - 1981-1983 (Box 8)
    - 1982-1987 (Box 8)
  - Gordon conference, 1976-1981 (Box 8)
  - Tulsa conference, 1981-1984 (Box 8)
- Reviews & evaluations, 1969-1997
  ALL FILES IN THIS SERIES ARE CLOSED TO RESEARCHERS AT THIS TIME.
  - Evaluation of President (Box 8)
    - Formal reports, 1978 (Box 8)
    - 1977-1979 (Box 8)
    - undated (Box 8)
  - Faculty Board of Review-Scrimgeour case, 1969 (Box 8)
  - Malik, Bary (Box 8)
    - 1971-1984 (Box 8)
    - 1977-1978 (Box 8)
  - Malik's case, 1971-1979 (Box 8)
  - Political science review (Box 9)
    - annual reports, 1991-1997 (Box 9)
    - 1996-1997 (Box 9)
  - Presidential Search (Box 9)
    - 1986 (Box 9)
    - 1987 (Box 9)
    - undated (Box 9)
  - Psychology Department review, 1993-1994 (Box 9)
  - Re Classified Research, 1968-1970 (Box 9)
  - Review Board, 1969-1970 (Box 9)
  - Review committee, Colorado, 1986-1987 (Box 9)
  - Review of Richard P. Gousha (Dean of budget) (Box 9)
    - 1979-1981 (Box 9)
    - undated (Box 9)
  - Review of English Department (Box 9)
    - 1979-1980 (Box 9)
    - Program Review Jan., 1980 (Box 9)
    - undated (Box 9)
  - Review of Physics Program in Louisiana (Box 9)
    - Committee materials, circa 1976 (Box 9)
    - Report from University of New Orleans, circa 1976 (Box 9)
    - Report from Tulane University, circa 1976 (Box 9)
    - Report from Louisiana State University, circa 1976 (Box 9)
  - Budget background (Box 9)
    - 1973-1975 (Box 9)
    - 1975 (Box 9)
    - 1976 (Box 9)
    - 1977 (Box 9)
    - 1978 (Box 9)
    - 1980 (Box 9)